Alright, so today we are on כריתות ג, Kritot Gimmel, three, and
we pick up on the bottom of דף ב עמוד ב, Daf
Bet Amud Bet, and we went through all the cases where other
משניות Mishnayot give numbers and we said what are the points of
these numbers, but with the emphasis on pointing out that the point
of the number in our משנה Mishnah is to tell you that
you can bring multiple חטאות Chataot even in one state of forgetfulness,
although not thirty-six because two of them are מצוות עשה Mitzvot Aseh
and רש"י Rashi later says it's thirty-four, but okay, and also that
we quickly saw all the other משניות Mishnayot from the rest of
the מסכת Masechet that spoke about different things of variations of the
theme of a קרבן חטאת, Korban Chatat, אשם תלוי, Asham Talui, מחוסרי
כפרה, Mechusrei Kaparah, and so on. Now we continue on the bottom
of דף ב עמוד ב Daf Bet Amud Bet with where אמר
מר, Amar Mar, it is about ten lines from the bottom, line
starts with the word ומפגל. Umefagel. Okay, not from the bottom, ten
lines before the lines get wide. So the גמרא Gemara says אמר
מר, Amar Mar, הביאום כולם בהעלם אחת חייב על כל אחת ואחת.
Hevi'um Kulam Behe'elam Achat Chayav Al Kol Achat Ve'achat. So this is
going to be our focus for today, that we said the purpose
of giving a number is to say that even if you did
them all in one state of forgetfulness, meaning somehow one state of
not remembering that you had a חיוב Chiyuv to do any of
these מצוות, Mitzvot, or any of these עבירות Aveirot I should say,
anyway, then you bring a separate קרבן Korban for each one. Now
that's the most obvious case because it's a separate act and a
separate עבירה. Aveira. But now we're going to discuss this issue about
when would you bring multiple קרבנות, Korbanot, when only one, if it
was in one state of forgetfulness. So the גמרא Gemara says בשלמא
פטור לגמרי לא מצית אמרת. Bishlama Patur Legamrei Lo Matzit Amart. First
we have to establish the idea that you bring multiple קרבנות Korbanot
in one state of forgetfulness. So I understand you're not going to
be exempt completely, which is of course
bizarre, if you did one you're חייב, Chayav, if you did thirty-six
you're פטור, Patur, but anyway the גמרא Gemara just says that's obvious
that you're not going to be exempt, דכתיב
כי כל אשר יעשה מכל התועבות האלה ונכרתו. Dechtiv Ki Kol Asher
Ya'aseh Mikol Hato'evot Ha'eleh Venichratu. Anybody that does of all of these
and really of any of these you'll be cut off, but certainly
if you do all of them, there's כרת Karet and if there's
כרת Karet there's going to be a חטאת. Chatat. So obviously if
you do multiple it doesn't make it any better. אלא אימא, Ela
Eima, but why don't I say that even if you do multiple,
עבר חדא נתחייב חדא עבר כולהו בהעלם אחת אינו חייב אלא אחת,
Avar Chada Nitchayev Chada Avar Kulhu Behe'elam Achat Eino Chayav Ela Achat,
that if you do one you bring one and if you do
all of them, if it's in one state of forgetfulness, then you
bring only one. Now by the way, let's say you did the
same עבירה Aveira multiple times, right? Let's say you forgot that it
was אסור Assur to cook on שבת Shabbat and you cooked five
times on שבת. Shabbat. So as long as it was one state
of forgetfulness, it's not like you remembered in between, oh right, they
told me I couldn't cook, and then you forgot again. But if
that didn't happen, it was one state of forgetfulness, you bring one
קרבן Korban as long as it was the same עבירה Aveira multiple
times in one state of forgetfulness. So the question is, maybe we
shouldn't limit it to that case? Maybe we should say even if
you do multiple different sins, as long as they're in the same
state of forgetfulness, it's only one קרבן. Korban. Where do you have
the basic principles that you bring multiple קרבנות Korbanot for separate sins
if it's in one state of forgetfulness? Charlie, you got a question?
Even if it's over multiple שבתות? Shabbatot? Right, that's correct. Well I
mean, is there already going to be a פסוק Pasuk מכל, Mikol,
how
do you know that you're not obligated unless you do all of
them?
Okay, I'm
sure that's a good question, but we learn, I mean, I think
that's from other פסוקים Psukim because our paradigm as we'll see will
be a קרבן Korban for עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah and there it
speaks about doing one sin and bringing a קרבן, Korban, so I
don't think that was ever a הוה אמינא. Hava Amina. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this, so how do I know,
maybe I should just say you always only bring one if it's
one state of forgetfulness? So the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבי יוחנן,
Amar Rabbi Yochanan, so רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says famous line here,
לכך יצאת כרת באחותו לחלק. Lekach Yatzat Karet Ba'achoto Lechaleik.
When the תורה Torah speaks about at the end of the פרשה
Parsha of אחרי מות Acharei Mot or קדושים, Kedoshim, one of those,
that you get for doing all of these עריות Arayot you get
כרת, Karet, כי כל אשר יעשה מכל התועבות האלה ונכרתו, Ki Kol
Asher Ya'aseh Mikol Hato'evot Ha'eleh Venichratu, so it says כרת Karet for
all of
them. But when it speaks about the prohibition of a man sleeping
with his sister, it explicitly says don't do this and you'll get
כרת. Karet. So the question is, why did the תורה Torah have
to say it specifically by the sister if it says a general
statement that if you do any of these you get כרת? Karet?
So this is what רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said, לכך יצאת כרת
באחותו, Lekach Yatzat Karet Ba'achoto, here's why the תורה Torah says a
man gets כרת Karet for sleeping with his sister even though we
knew it was part of the general rule, in order to tell
you that every one is taken individually. So אחותו Achoto is distinct
from the other ones and the same is true, every single thing
is taken individually and כרת Karet means the assumption of כרת, Karet,
the implied point of כרת Karet is that you'll bring a חטאת
Chatat if it's בשוגג. Beshogeg. So it told you that to tell
you the idea of treat each one separately and therefore you will
bring multiple חטאות. Chataot. לכך יצאת כרת באחותו לחלק, Lekach Yatzat Karet
Ba'achoto Lechaleik, to make to distinguish it, or not just it, to
make each one distinct. So מתיב ליה רבי ביבי בר אביי, Metiv
Lei Rabbi Bibi Bar Abaye, so רבי ביבי בר אביי Rabbi Bibi
Bar Abaye asked on the רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan statement, אימא אחותו
דפרט קרא נתחייב חטאת עלה, Eima Achoto Deparat Kra Nitchayev Chatat Alah,
maybe we should say this is unique to an אחותו, Achoto, an
אחותו Achoto that the תורה Torah says a separate כרת, Karet, there
you'll get a separate
קרבן, Korban, וכולן, Vechulan, and all
of them... חטאת chatas *chatas*, but maybe everything else doesn't bring a
separate חטאת chatas *chatas* if you do multiple different sins. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, what type of what type of suggestion is
that? והא דרב ביבי בר אביי Abaye *Veha deRav Bibi bar Abaye*
is לית ליה *lais leh*? What, you never heard of the general
principle? כל דבר שהיה בכלל ויצא מן הכלל ללמד לא ללמד על
עצמו יצא אלא ela ללמד על הכלל כולו יצא *Kol davar shehayah
bichlal veyatza min haklal lelamed lo lelamed al atzmo yatza ela lelamed
al haklal kulo yatza*? That anything that was part of a category,
it was taken out and a special rule was said by it,
you don't treat it as an exception, you treat it לא ללמד
על עצמו יצא *lo lelamed al atzmo yatza*. It's not an exception,
but you're to treat it as a paradigm. You learn from that
to the entire category. So by אחותו achoto *achoso* you bring a
separate חטאת chatas, *chatas*, then that case tells you by everything in
the category you bring a separate חטאת chatas. *chatas*. Where do we
know this principle that when one thing has a separate law is
applied, you assume it applies to everything in the category? כיצד *Keitzad*,
what's an example of this? והנפש אשר תאכל בשר מזבח השלמים אשר
לה' וטומאתו עליו ונכרתה *Vehanefesh asher tochal basar mizevach hashelamim asher l'Hashem
vetumaso alav venichresa*. So this is talking about if a person is
טמא *tamei* and eats from קרבנות korbanos, *korbanos* you get כרת kares
*kares*, and it specifically spells it out by שלמים *shelamim*. So it
says שלמים בכלל כל הקדשים היו *shelamim bichlal kol hakodashim hayu*. שלמים
*Shelamim* was in all the other קרבנות korbanot? *korbanos*. למה יצאו *Lama
yatze-u*?
Why
were they singled out, why was שלמים *shelamim* singled out to tell
you this idea that a man gets כרת kares *kares* if he
eats from שלמים *shelamim*? להקיש עליהם *Lehakish aleihem*, to connect to them,
meaning to use it as a as a lesson, as a paradigm.
מה שלמים שהם קדשי מזבח וחייבין עליהן *Mah shelamim shehem kodshei mizbe-ach
vechayavin aleihen*, when where do you get כרת kares *kares*? If you
are טמא *tamei* and you eat something like a שלמים *shelamim*, which
is a קרבן korban *korban*, then אף כל קדשי מזבח חייבין עליהן
*af kol kodshei mizbe-ach chayavin aleihen*. So therefore we say the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* that says you get כרת kares? *kares* for eating from
something says that you eat from קדשי ה' *kodshei Hashem*, right? It
does not say a קרבן Korban *korban* explicitly. And then it explicitly
says שלמים *shelamim*. So why what do we learn from שלמים *shelamim*?
It's not true about eating anything that's holy, it's only true about
eating קרבנות *korbanos*. We don't say it's only true about שלמים *shelamim*,
we say it's only true about eating קרבנות *korbanos*. One minute. יצאו
קדשי בדק הבית *Yatze-u kodshei bedek habayis*, it excludes something that is
sanctified for the temple treasury, that you are not do not get
כרת kares *kares* if you are טמא *tamei*. Now, there's still a
separate problem of מעילה *me'ilah*, we'll discuss that when we get to
our מסכת מעילה *Masechet Me'ilah*, but in terms of the problem about
being טמא *tamei*, that's a problem of just eating from it. But
the specific problem of being טמא *tamei*, that is only a problem
by קרבנות *korbanos*. So what do you see? When something is singled
out, it teaches you about the category. We don't say it only
applies to that thing. So here too. So אמר ליה רב ביבי
בר מיניה *amar leh Rav Bibi bar minei* says no, that's not
a relevant point. לאו lav, מי אמרת *Lav mi amarta*, okay, I
accept that something teaches a rule, but you the rule you use
that thing as a paradigm. So what's the paradigm? מי אמרת התם
יצאו קדשי בדק הבית *Mi amarta hasam yatze-u kodshei bedek habayis* from
שלמים *shelamim* in that case, you learn to exclude things that are
for the temple treasury. הכא נמי *Hacha nami*, מה אחותו achoto? מיוחדת
שהיא ערוה *mah achoso meyuchades shehi ervah*, maybe I'll say okay, anything
like sister has a separate קרבן Korban *korban*. Not not only sister,
everything like sister. It's a paradigm. Fine. What's like sister? Here's what's
like sister. Number one, it's עריות arayos *arayos*. So things that aren't
עריות Arayot? *arayos* maybe don't get a separate קרבן korban, *korban*. Number
one. Number two, ואין לה היתר בחיי אוסרה *ve-ein lah heter bechayei
osrah*. She is a sister will never be allowed what when will
never be alive will never be will never be מותר Mutar. *mutar*,
right, in the life of the person that makes her forbidden. Now
who like makes her I guess you do, your brother, or maybe
but anyway, so she she will there's never a way in which
your sister will be permissible to you. אף כל שאין לה היתר
בחיי אוסרה *Af kol she-ein lah heter bechayei osrah*, that would be
true by all the other thing all the other women that are
like that, which are you know, most of the עריות Arayot, *arayos*
don't remain can do not become won't have a state of being
permitted. But not all of them. יצאה אשת איש שיש לה היתר
בחיי בעלה *Yatza-ah eshes ish sheyesh lah heter bechayei ba-alah*. How about
a married woman? A married woman could become permissible. So therefore maybe
it wouldn't be included. So he says look, fine, I'll accept אחותו
achoto. *achoso* is a paradigm. But it's not going to tell you
every single כרת kares *kares*, it'll only tell you עריות *arayos* and
maybe not even עריות *arayos*, maybe only the עריות *arayos* that are
permanently forbidden, not an ערוה *ervah* that can become permissible, like a
married woman. So therefore I still don't know the idea that every
single separate act that you get כרת kares *kares*, you would bring
you would bring a separate חטאת chatas *chatas* if it was in
one state of forgetfulness. Where do I know that from? So אמר
רבי יונה ואיתימא רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע אמר קרא *amar Rabbi
Yona ve-isayma Rav Huna breih deRav Yehoshua amar kra*, because the verse
says כי כל אשר יעשה מכל התועבות האל ונכרתו *ki kol asher
ya-aseh mikol hato-evos ha-eil venichresu*. So anybody does any of these things
will be cut off and that's the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* at the
end that says you get כרת kares, *kares* for any of the
עריות *arayos*. So הוקשו כל העריות כולן לאחותו *hukshu kol ha-arayos kulan
l'achoso*. All the עריות *arayos* are explicitly connected. Okay, so there a
פסוק posuk? *pasuk* was and it doesn't just happen to be that
they're that they're treated as a category. It explicitly says they all
get כרת kares. *kares* and it and treats them all as a
group. So therefore that tells you that you treat them all completely
equally when it comes to כרת kares *kares*. So מה אחותו achoto
חייב עליה בפני עצמה אף כל חייב עליה בפני עצמה *mah achoso
chayav aleiha bifnei atzmah af kol chayav aleiha bifnei atzmah*. So therefore
it tells you it's not like אחותו achoto? *achoso* you look at
the unique characteristics of אחותו achoto *achoso*. No. There it says they're
all the same when it comes to כרת kares *kares* so you
get a separate חטאת Chatat. *chatas* for each one. Now what it
doesn't tell us is how do we know to apply this outside
of the עריות *arayos*? Somehow the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*... assumes that once
you are no longer making it specifically about אחותו, achoso then you
can generalize, but you know you could have raised that question as
well. But here the גמרא Gemara basically with the idea of אחותו
achoso plus the explicit פסוק posuk that links it to everything else
says from that we learn that a separate קרבן korban for each
one. Now why does it say כרת kares specifically by אחותו?
achoso No,
first you have to learn you get a separate one, and then
you have to apply it equally plus what? Why? Where should it
have said it?
No, I'm just asking. I don't know. Okay, but it also says,
but
the point is it says ואיש אשר ישכב את אשה נדה וגלה
את ערותה וגו' Ve'ish asher yishkav et ishah nidah vegilah et ervatah
vego' וכרתו שניהם venichretu sheneihem also. Right. So it doesn't just say
כרת kares. by אחותו. achoso Right. So then maybe you have two
things and don't you have different rules by that? Because not, if
you have one thing you can say לאו למידה אתא, lav lemida
ata, but then if you have two things?
Right. That is a good question and I believe I'll get back
to you because this idea of למה יצאת כרת באחותו lama yatzat
kares be'achoto is in a couple of גמרות Gemoras and I believe
in some places the issue about why specifically it had to say
כרת kares by נדה nidah is addressed. It's not addressed in our
גמרא, Gemara but the גמרא Gemara does address it, so I will
get back to you on that. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like
this: לרבי יצחק דאמר חייבי כריתות בכלל היו ולמה יצאת כרת באחותו
לדון בכרת ולא במלקות. Le'Rabbi Yitzchak de'amar chayvei keritot bikhlal hayu velama
yatzat kares be'achoto ladun bekares velo bemalkut. One minute. We have another
opinion out there we haven't quoted yet, now we're quoting, that says
that there's a separate thing you learn from כרת באחותו. kares be'achoto.
What do you learn? This is a general question in מכות Makkot
which is: everything that's a חייב כרת, chayav kares, it all, well
some of them are חייב מיתה chayav mitah if there's warning, but
some of them it's not חייב מיתה chayav mitah but it's a
transgression of a לאו, lav, so it's חייב מלקות. chayav malkut. So
which do you get? Somebody did something willfully, they warned this person
about מלקות. malkut. So do you say, oh no, we're not going
to give you מלקות, malkut, you get כרת? kareis No. Normally the
general idea is that the תורה Torah gives עונש onesh to, you
know, to בית דין Beit Din to be done in this world
and these and therefore you do them in this world. You don't
say, oh you're getting כרת kareis. anyway, we're not going to give
you מלקות. malkut. Fine. So you give the guy מלקות. malkut. Now
what's the story? Does he, is he still going to get כרת
kareis. by God or not? So there's a fascinating
מחלוקת. machloket. Some say כל חייבי כריתות שלקו נפטרו מידי כריתתן, kol
chayvei keritot shelaku nifteru miyedei keritatan, that no, the whole idea is
you get a this-world punishment and therefore you are now cleansed of
your sin and you don't get כרת kareis, anymore. But here there's
the opinion of רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak that says no. He says
למה יצאת כרת באחותו לדון בכרת ולא במלקות. lama yatzat kares be'achoto
ladun bekares velo bemalkut. To tell you that you're, now that doesn't
mean you don't get מלקות, malkut, but to tell you that you're
going to get כרת, kareis you're not going to get off the
hook for your מלקות malkut from because of your מלקות. malkut. Even
if you get מלקות, malkut, you still are going to get כרת.
kareis. I mean you could do תשובה teshuvah or whatever, but the
מלקות malkut is not going to be sufficient to get you off
of כרת kareis. and therefore the תורה Torah emphasizes, you know, doubly
emphasizes כרת kareis. to tell you this כרת Kareth sticks. מלקות malkut
won't get you off the hook. Okay, so that's what he learns
from it. Now not to tell you that we don't פסקן pasken
like that, we פסקן pasken that מלקות malkut gets you off of
כרת. Kareth, But anyway, the point is, how do we know, how
do we פסקן? pasken? Okay, I understand. Anyway, all right, fine. Anyway,
the גמרא Gemara now says though, but then he doesn't have
אחותו achoso extra. How does he learn a separate חטאת Chatat for
each one? So the
גמרא Gemara, says: לחלק מנא ליה? lechaleik mena leh? How does he
know a separate חטאת Chatat, for each
one? So the גמרא Gemara says: נפקא ליה מואל אשה בנדת טומאתה.
nafka leh me've'el ishah benidat tumatah. There you go, Michael. A woman
who is a
נדה, nidah, לא תקרב, lo tikrav, לחלק על כל אשה ואשה. lechaleik
al kol ishah ve'ishah. So to tell you ואל אשה, ve'el ishah,
so the אשה ishah is, but here it's not just the fact
of כרת Kareth, itself, it seems to be the specific emphasis of
ואל אשה. ve'el ishah. Why did it say ואל אשה? ve'el ishah?
רש"י Rashi just said why didn't it just say ואל נדה? ve'el
nidah? Now I should note by the way that while in rabbinic
literature נדה nidah is the name for the woman who is menstruating,
in the תורה, Torah, נדה nidah is always a verb and or
a sort of a, what do you call it, a gerund or
something. Anyway, but it is not a, it does not describe the
person. A woman during her period of flow, a woman who has
a flow. It refers to the flow, not the woman. But the
גמרא, Gemara at least the way רש"י Rashi understands seeing it through
its eyes where נדה nidah describes the woman, says why does the
פסוק posuk go out and say the woman if it could have
just said the נדה? nidah? And therefore says to tell you that
every woman is treated separately, every עריות is treated
separately. לחלק על כל אשה ואשה. lechaleik al kol ishah ve'ishah. So
the גמרא Gemara says: רבנן נמי תיפוק ליה מואל אשה בנדת טומאתה?
rabbanan nami tipok leh me've'el ishah benidat tumatah? Why not learn it
from the extra word אשה? ishah? Why learn it from אחותו? achoso
So אי הכי נמי, ee hachi nami, yeah you're right. Fine, they
do learn it from that. אלא כרת דאחותו למה אתא? ela kares
de'achoto lema ata? Why is it telling you כרת באחותו? kares be'achoto?
Which is funny because normally the one that's quoted is the רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan line, כרת באחותו kares be'achoto is לחלק. lechaleik. But
now we're saying, oh no, that you could have learned out from
אשה. ishah. So what do you learn out from
כרת באחותו? kares be'achoto? מיבעי ליה לחלק על אחותו ועל אחות אביו
ועל אחות אמו. mibaei leh lechaleik al achoto ve'al achot aviv ve'al
achot immo. So it says let's say you have three separate sins,
but they're all somewhat, somewhat of the same category. Your sister, your
father's sister, your mother's sister. Now we would not think that your
sister and your father's sister are exactly the same category, but anyway,
the גמרא Gemara says they're all somewhat, it's all about being a
sister. So therefore maybe if you did those three in one state
of forgetfulness it's only one חטאת, Chatat. although there's three separate acts
with three separate people, but they're all sister
sins. So therefore it had to say by אחותו Achoto to emphasize
this idea that no, no, no, each one is different. So the
גמרא Gemara says, הני למה לי לחלק? hani lama li l'chalek? Why
do you need a
פסוק? posuk הרי שמות מחולקים וגופות מחולקים. harei shemos mekhulakim v'guphos mekhulakim.
They're separate sins. These are the important key terms. שמות מחולקים, shemos
mekhulakim, which means a separate לאו, lav a separate prohibition, and גופי
מחולקים, guphi mekhulakim, a separate person, meaning or sometimes גופי מחולקים guphi
mekhulakim isn't always about a person. Let's say it's eating חלב chelev
and דם. dam. It's גופי מחולקים, guphi mekhulakim, okay? But there everything
makes those distinct acts, distinct different people and different עבירות. aveiros. So
you don't need a פסוק posuk, for that. So אלא אימא, ella
eima, okay fine, here's what you needed the פסוק posuk for. לחלק
על אחותו שהיא אחות אביו ושהיא אחות אמו. l'chalek al achoso shehi
achos aviv v'shehi achos imo.
No, no, no, no, no, that's what I thought it meant first
when you read it. But no, it's saying let's say you have
somebody who's both your sister and your father's sister and your mother's
sister. Somebody who's your sister and your aunt. Now, it's a little
hard to imagine how you get that case. I'm not going to
go into details. That's a יבמות Yevamos discussion, okay? It would require
a lot of creativity in terms of a lot of sins in
order to get somebody who's both your sister and your aunt. But
let's say you had somebody who is your sister and your father's
sister and your mother's sister. Let's say you have somebody that is
all those people. So it's not גופי מחולקים. guphi mekhulakim. It's one
person. It is different sins, but they're all sister sins. So maybe
that would only be one חטאת. Chatat So how do you know
that? So you know that from the extra word of אחותו achoso.
to tell you no, even there you bring multiple חטאות. chatas. Which
basically teaches you the principle that even things that are one person
or one object or whatever it is, if they're separate sins, even
if closely related sins, then they and
she's a נדה niddah at the same time.
All right, fine.
No, no, yes, right, yes,
that's what we just said.
Six? Would be six, I guess. What do you mean six?
No, would it be no,
there's one person, there's three, one person, there's four, yeah.
רבי יצחק, Rabbi Yitzchak, הא מילתא מנא ליה? ha milsa minalei? So
where does רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak get this idea? Now again, while
it seems to be an absurd case, it is telling you an
important principle. That to define things for a separate חטאת Chatat does
not require a separate act. It's even one act, it's sufficient if
they are considered separate sins. So where does רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak
know this since he does not have אחותו achoso? as an extra
word? So where does he know this
from? So נפקא ליה מסיפא דקרא. naflei mi'seifa d'kra. דכתיב ערבת אחותו
גילה. d'ksiv ervas achoso gilah. After it says you get כרת Kareth
for your sister, it once again repeats he uncovered the nakedness of
his sister. Okay, so therefore that why that's redundant? So again, the
extra אחותו achoso there is to tell you this idea of distinguishing
the
acts. ורבנן, v'rabbanan, what do they do? אחותו דסיפא דקרא מאי עביד
להו? achoso d'seifa d'kra mai avid lehu? What do they do with
it? מיבעי ליה, mibayei lei, אביי וג' אמר, abayei v'gimmel amar, oh
finally, מיבעי ליה לאחותו שהיא בת אביו ובת אמו לומר שאין עונשין
מן הדין. mibayei lei l'achoso shehi bas aviv u'vas imo, lomar she'ein
onshin min hadin. This is what Michael thought before. To tell you
another thing, which is this is quite bizarre, but or ironic, but
the Torah says a man cannot sleep with his sister through his
father or his sister through his
mother. Meaning what about his full sister? Through his father and mother?
Now you would say, wait a minute, isn't that also the sister
of his father? So interestingly, it's not just a קל וחומר. kal
v'chomer. It is that thing, right? It's like
בכלל מאתיים מנה. b'khlal masayim maneh. If you you know, it's like
if I owe you 200, I owe you 100. That's not a
קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. That's implicit in the first statement, right? So
if you can't a man can't sleep with his sister on his
mother's side, he can't sleep with his whole sister, that is his
sister. But the גמרא Gemara assumes not that way. The גמרא Gemara
assumes that it is a conceptually different category. One is half sister,
the other is full sister. And therefore, I would not it's not
automatically inferred from the first case. It's a קל וחומר, kal v'chomer,
but it's not it is not an application of the first case.
And therefore, I need to learn it out. So okay, learn it
out from a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. No, we have a principle
אין עונשין מן הדין. ein onshin min hadin. You can't punish somebody
based on logic, based on קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. You need a
פסוק Pasuk, to tell me you get כרת. Kareth A קל וחומר
kal v'chomer won't tell me you get כרת. Kareth. So therefore the
extra אחותו achoso? is to tell me the idea of full sister.
For a full sister, which is considered a different category, even though
it's a קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, you need אחותו achoso? to tell
me you get כרת, Kareth לומר שאין עונשין מן הדין. lomar she'ein
onshin min hadin. You cannot get כרת Kareth with just based on
a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. And the גמרא Gemara says for רבי
יצחק, Rabbi Yitzchak, now רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak that uses has one
less אחותו because he's using it to tell you this idea that
מלקות malkus doesn't get you off of כרת. Kareth So where does
he know a full sister? סבר עונשין מן הדין. savar onshin min
hadin. All right, he says you can get you can learn punishment
from a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. He doesn't buy into that general
principle. ואיבעית אימא, v'iba'is eima, if you don't like that, יליף עונש
מאזהרה. yalif ones me'azhara. Since there is a פסוק, pasuk, which we're
not going to get into, where we learn that a full sister
is prohibited, okay, meaning we do learn from a פסוק pasuk. that
a full sister's prohibited. The only thing that was not said explicitly
in the Torah is that a full sister gets כרת. Kareth. So
he can say fine, so the same way a full sister is
like a half sister for the prohibition, a full sister is like
a half sister for כרת. Kareth, Now you would say okay, but
you're still deriving it. But here the גמרא Gemara says the only
thing you cannot learn out that you get a punishment for is
קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, is pure logic. Now on the one hand
that's ironic, right? You would think
the
גמרא Gemara says קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. Yes, and because it is
so logical, you know, logic isn't always isn't always correct, meaning not
just that you're making a mistake in logic, but you know, at
the end of the day this is like a divine system and
even if logically we derive something, you know, and there's a compelling
logic of קל וחומר, Kal V'Chomer, what how far can we go
but just based on our own pure human logic? So there are
limits, אין עונשין מן הדין. Ein Onshin Min HaDin. Okay, but that
but if you can learn out the idea of עונש Onesh through
a sort of more formalistic thing, like a היקש, Hekesh, גזירה שוה,
Gzeirah Shavah, and so on, on the one hand because those are
less logical, you need a tradition for most of those, there's a
debate how many you need a tradition for, but anyway, but that's
also why there's the I think a the point here is like
a greater sense of confidence in the conclusion, or a greater sense
of how far you can go in the conclusion. So therefore, if
you learn it out from the fact of a היקש, Hekesh, since
they're connected to the prohibition, they will be connected also for the
for the punishment, that you can do, that's not a pure that's
not קל וחומר, Kal V'Chomer, that's not just pure logic, there there
actually is there's some of these more formalistic rules, and there you're
allowed to take them a little bit further. Okay, a little bit
more odd about it, as
you would think of of אין עונשין מן הדין Ein Onshin Min
HaDin in the context of a court administered punishment, you know, rules,
right? I mean, God can be can punish you בדין. B'Din.
Right, right, that is a good
that
is an excellent point, so it goes back to the point before,
which is the question about like, what do you mean you פוסק,
Posek, you פטור Patur from כרת Kareth, or not? Now, well, but
then that calls into
question the whole enterprise, like why even list them all?
Right, right, well, so that's what I was sort of going to
say, the נפקא מינה Nafka Mina of this is, is that if
you can't prove כרת, Kareth then you also can't be מחייב חטאת.
Mechayev Chatat. So there's a נפקא מינה Nafka Mina of saying that
we legitimately can know sort of as far as the system is
concerned that you get כרת, Kareth. right? Whether God is what God
is going to do, you know, I'm sure God has complete discretion
and can waive your כרת Kareth or you know whatever based on
God's considerations. But as far as we're concerned, we have to know
if you're called a חייב כרת Chayav Kareth in order for the
implications of being a חטאת. chatas So that seems to be the
implication, but you're right, it is a definitely a an interesting extension
of the idea of אין עונשין מן הדין. Ein Onshin Min HaDin.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so that's how we
sort of work the whole thing out. So but at the end
of the day we learn separate קרבן korban for each separate act,
even if it's one act and multiple sins, multiple שמות, Shemot, a
separate קרבן and this interesting thing about full sister. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara goes on to say the following.
Is that why we have it repeated in אחרי מות קדושים Acharei
Mot Kedoshim because of all these different, you know?
Well, no, the repetition is because in one of them it's the
prohibition and the other it's the punishment. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, אמר רבי
אלעזר אמר רבי הושעיא, Amar Rabbi Elazar Amar Rabbi Oshaya, כל מקום
שאתה מוצא שני לאוין וכרת אחד. Kol makom she'ata motzei shnei lavin
v'kareth echad. Now we're really going to get to the heart of
trying to define the parameters of multiple חטאות. Chataot.
So
he says like this, let's say in the פסוקים, Psukim, before now
we were talking about learning multiple acts or a single act, multiple
sins, how about if in the פסוקים Psukim it's not explicit doesn't
treat the two things as completely separate?
Let's
say you have two prohibitions but it only says כרת Kareth? once
for the two things. Don't do this, don't do that, if you
do either of these you'll get כרת. Kareth Okay, it doesn't say
a separate כרת Kareth. for each one. Is that enough to tell
me, now again, I will get כרת karet. for doing both of
them, but this is again within the חטאת chatas context, that if
I do both of them in one state of forgetfulness, they're considered
sufficiently distinct that I will bring two separate חטאות. Chataot. If it
only says כרת karet. in for for you know for them as
a group, for them as like if you do either you get
כרת. karet, So he says כל מקום שאתה מוצא. Kol makom she'ata
motzei.
Is this an example with all the עריות?
No, we'll see the one example of this. כל מקום שאתה מוצא
שני לאוין וכרת אחד, Kol makom she'ata motzei shnei lavin v'kareth echad,
if there's two לאוין Lavin and one כרת, karet, so חילק חטאות
ביניהם. Chilek chataot beineihem. Don't think that means that it's only one
חטאת, chatas, no, each one gets a distinctive חטאת. chatas. Now, Michael,
you're right, in a way it says that all by all the
עריות, but there we have אחותו to basically tell me treat each
one separately. But let's say it's not that case. It's a separate
case that you get two prohibitions but one כרת, karet. nevertheless, they're
sufficiently distinct that you will bring two חטאות. Chataot. ומהי היא, U'mai
hi, what's the case where we have this? מפטם וסך, Mifatem v'sach,
if somebody basically makes the שמן המשחה Shemen HaMishchah and puts it
on his skin, or puts the one from the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash on his skin. וכתיב, U'chtiv, here's the
פסוק, pasuk. על בשר אדם לא ייסך ובמתכונתו לא תעשו כמהו, Al
b'sar adam lo yisach u'v'matkunto lo ta'asu kamohu, do not put the
שמן המשחה Shemen HaMishchah from the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, the anointing
oil, on your skin, do not also make your own according to
the same proportions. So that's separate prohibitions, it says
לא ייסך, Lo yisach, לא תעשו כמהו, Lo ta'asu kamohu, separate prohibitions,
but then what does it say at the end? וכרת אחד, V'kareth
echad, it only says כרת karet, once, דכתיב, Dechtiv, איש אשר ירקח
כמהו ואשר יתן ממנו על זר ונכרת מעמיו, Ish asher yirkach kamohu
v'asher yitein mimenu al zar v'nichrat mei'amav, if you do this or
that you'll get כרת. karet. So it's only כרת karet once for
both of them. So maybe if I did both of them in
one state of forgetfulness it'll only be one חטאת chatat, because only
one כרת? karet So here כרת karet. is the trans translates into
חטאת chatat. when it is שוגג, Shogeg, that is why we're focusing
on כרת. karet, So גמרא Gemara says, that's what I learn out
to
tell
me to. that's basically obvious. וכי מאחר דלאוין מחולקים כרת אחותו דכתב
רחמנא למה לי? vechi me'achar delavin mechulakim karet achoso dechasav rachamana lama
li? If you buy into that statement, then why did we need
this whole discussion
earlier? וכי מאחר דלאוין מחולקים כרת אחותו דכתב רחמנא למה לי? vechi
me'achar delavin mechulakim karet achoso dechasav rachamana lama li? If you tell
me this principle, now the funny thing is, that Rabbi Elazar in
the name of Rabbi Oshaya never told me where he got this
principle. Maybe he only got built this principle on the פסוקים pesukim
before of אחותו. So it's a little strange. גמרא Gemara says, okay,
but if your principle is true and somehow we know it a
priori, that separate לאוין lavin means separate קרבנות, so who needs that
whole earlier discussion about אחותו? Right? Like רש"י Rashi said, you know,
that's the same thing, everything has a separate לאו lav is one
big כרת. kares, We said you need אחותו to divide it. If
you're telling me you have an a priori principle that a separate
לאו lav, is sufficient for a separate קרבן, so who needed that
whole earlier discussion? So the גמרא Gemara says, why did we need
אחותו? כרת אחותו למה לי? karet achoso lama li? ורבי יצחק כדית
ליה ולרבנן מיבעי ליה למימר שאין עונשין מן הדין. ve'Rabbi Yitzchak kide'is
lei u'lerabbanan mibayei lei lemeimar she'ein onshin min hadin. Okay, so there's
a big parenthesis here which they say is a later gloss, which
doesn't really fit, but basically the answer is, no, we needed to
tell me the things it taught me. What did it teach me?
According to רבי יצחק, Rabbi Yitzchak, it taught me the principle of
that if you get מלכות, malkus, you don't get off the hook
for כרת. kares And according to the רבנן, Rabbanan, it taught me
this principle of somebody or it was needed to teach me about
a full sister, you also get punishment, not a half sister. Okay,
but what about we also said that it was needed, you know,
לא אחותו, lo achoso, the אשה ishah by נדה, niddah, anyway, one
of those things was also needed to teach me separate חטאות. chataos.
So here what the גמרא Gemara seems to be saying, the way
רש"י Rashi understands it, is fine, at the end of the day,
really those פסוקים pesukim were needed to teach me something else. We
threw in that idea of separate חטאות, chataos, but you're right, according
to the principle you just laid down, we don't need it. Okay,
now this is again, as I said, it's a very strange גמרא
Gemara because the real question is, where does רבי אלעזר אמר רבי
אושעיא Rabbi Elazar amar Rabbi Oshaya know his principle from? Where does
he know that if it's separate לאוין lavin in one כרת, it's
only one thing? And now that the גמרא Gemara turns and says,
oh, once you say that principle, who needed אחותו? If anything, you
would say maybe he just learned his principle from the earlier discussion.
Okay, either way though, that's what we have. We have now that
as long as it is separate sins, even if it's one act,
and not only that, even if the תורה Torah only assigns one
כרת, as long as it gives it different prohibitions, all those things
will be separate חטאות. chataos. Now the גמרא gemara continues after the
parenthesis. אמר רב נתן בר יצחק אף אנן נמי תנינא. Amar Rav
Natan bar Yitzchak af anan nami tanina. We learn this further from
our משנה, Mishnah, this idea that there are separate חטאות chataos by
this case of מפטם mefatem and סך. sach. How do you know
this? Because our משנה Mishnah says, המפטם את השמן, hamfatem es hashemen,
if somebody makes the according to the proportions of the anointing oil,
the שמן המשחה, shemen hamishchah, המפטם את הקטורת, hamfatem es haktoret, or
makes according to the same proportions of the of the קטורת, ktoret,
of the
incense, והסך בשמן המשחה, vehasach beshemen hamishchah, or if you somebody anoints
the actual oil from the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash itself. Again, not
you anointed the oil you made at home, which you were transgressing,
but you anointed the oil from the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Anyway,
all of those are in the list of כרת. But it says,
one minute, that's a bizarre way of listing it. Why didn't it
put the two cases of the oil together, right? למה לי דתניא,
lama li detanya, should be
דתנא, detana, למה לי דתנא המפטם את הקטורת במציעא? lama li detana
hamfatem es haktoret bemetzia? Why did it separate the two cases of
the oil and put the case of making the incense between? Making
the oil, making the incense, or anointing the oil. That's a strange
order. So why did it do that? לאו הא קמשמע לן, lav
ha kamashma lan, it must be to tell
you, מה קטורת לאו בפני עצמו וחייבין עליה, mah ktoret lav bifnei
atzmo vechayavin aleha, that the same way, it's funny, the language here
is like language that uses when it makes a דרשה drasha on
a פסוק, pasuk but anyway, it's doing a דרשה drasha on the
משנה. Mishnah. But it's to tell me that the same way קטורת
ktoret is a separate
חטאת chatat because it's a separate לאו, so כרת בפני עצמו karet
bifnei atzmo and it has its own
כרת, אף מפטם שמן וסך נמי, af mefatem shemen vesach nami, so
the same is true about the making of the oil and the
anointing of the oil, דלאו בפני עצמו, delav bifnei atzmo, that because
they're separate prohibitions, חייבין עליה בפני עצמו, chayavin aleha bifnei atzmo, you
get a separate חטאת chatat? even if they're only one כרת. So
basically it says the fact that the משנה Mishnah went out of
its way to separate the two cases of the oil is to
emphasize that although it knows that there's only one כרת in the
תורה, Torah, but to emphasize to you that each one is distinct,
there'll be a separate חטאת, chatat just like קטורת ktoret is separate,
each one of these is a separate חטאת. chatat So it's implicit
in the משנה, Mishnah, the משנה Mishnah is emphasizing these are distinct
by putting the case of קטורת ktoret between
them. Now, וכי תימא דקבעי למתני פיטומים בהדי הדדי, vechi teima dekaba'ei
lemasni pitumim bahadi hadadei, if you'll say, no, no, the reason it
put קטורת ktoret in the middle was it wanted to combine not
the cases of oil and oil, but the cases of making stuff
at home. So making your oil, making your קטורת. ktoret. So that's
why it combined it. So the גמרא gemara says, no, that's not
a good
answer. ליתני איפכא, lisni ipcha, it could have just reversed the order.
It could have said, המפטם את הקטורת, hamfatem es haktoret, if you
make the קטורת ktoret at home, or המפטם את השמן, hamfatem es
hashemen, or you make the oil, והסך בשמן המשחה, vehasach beshemen hamishchah,
or if you anointed the oil. So it still could have combined
the cases of making it home and still juxtaposed the two cases
of the oil. אמאי פלגי לשמן *Amai palgei l'shemen*? Why did it
divide the two cases of oil? לאו הא קמשמע לן *Lav ha
kamashma lan*, to tell you דיש חילוק חטאות chataot ביניהם *deyesh chiluk
chataot beneihem*, each one is a separate חטאת chatat. *chatat*. שמע מינה
shema mina. *Shma mina*. That's good proof. Now of course what's a
little interesting is it was a very nice דיוק *diyuk* from the
language of the משנה mishna. *Mishna*, but you could have said if
the whole point of the משנה mishna *Mishna* of listing thirty-four is
to tell you thirty-four חטאות chataot. *chataot*, then it's implicit from that
point already, right? Because the whole point is to tell you there's
a separate חטאת chatat. *chatat* for everything mentioned in the משנה mishna
*Mishna*. But as we're going to continue to see, the idea that
the משנה mishna *Mishna* is telling you an exact number of חטאות
chataot *chataot*, it's only not telling you thirty-six anyway because two are
מצות עשה mitzvot asei. *mitzvot asei*. Anyway, that's going to be a
little bit questioned as we continue. So whether the משנה mishna *Mishna*
is telling you an exact number of חטאות chataot *chataot*. So therefore
he's going out of his way to point out that not just
the fact that by implicitly it's saying that there are separate חטאות
chataot *chataot* here, because maybe you could debate that, but the very
fact that it's the order that it's giving is a strange order
is to underscore that each one of these is distinct for the
purpose of the חטאת chatat. *chatat*. So now we have again the
idea of multiple חטאות chataot, *chataot*. So far the only case that
we would exclude is you did ממש *mamash* the same thing multiple
times in one state of forgetfulness. But if it's different sins, even
if it's the same person and object or whatever, and even if
it is the one כרת *karet* assigned in the תורה Torah, *Torah*,
as long as they're separate sins, then and even done in one
action, you will bring multiple חטאות chataot. *chataot*. So that is our
rule for now. Yes.
And it goes back to the case of the נדה *niddah* with
multiple...
okay, that's just an example also of multiple people, multiple sins even
done in the same action and with the
same person. What?
Same sin repeated.
What do you mean? If a person does נדה *niddah* multiple times
with one state of forgetfulness, it's one חטאת chatat *chatat*.
No, but if your sister and
a נדה *niddah*, so it's still just one...
it's different sins. No, a person sleeps with his
sister who is a נדה *niddah*, two חטאות chata'ot. *chataot*. Oh, so
but if he sleeps with two different...
each one is a separate לאו *lav*. If you have two wives
and you sleep with both of them when they're both נדה *niddah*,
that... okay, so that's an excellent question. That's גופי מחולקים *gufi mecholakim*
but שם אחת *shem achat*.
That was briefly mentioned...
no, we have not yet had גופי מחולקים ושם אחת *gufi mecholakim
v'shem achat*. We have גופי מחולקים ושמות מחולקים *gufi mecholakim v'shemos mecholakim*.
We have not yet done with that question of גופי מחולקים ושם
אחת *gufi mecholakim v'shem achat*. Okay, so we will get to that.
Okay? Right? Everybody understands the question he's asking is same sin but
that it involves a different act, different people. Okay, so that we
will discuss, but about whether that is enough to say separate חטאות
chata'ot. *chataot*.
Yes, I just want to go back to something you said before,
I'm not sure that I understand. So I'm understanding that, you know,
given his principle, it was Rabbi Elazar's principle, which we don't know
from where he derives it, but then our question was what do
we have that whole discussion for beforehand? And we said, no, it's
because of full sisters or whatever it was.
Meaning tell us one of the things was a חידוש *chiddush* and
the rest was just wasn't really necessary, but once the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* is needed to tell you one thing, it tells you other
things as well.
That's the way רש"י Rashi *Rashi* explains it. That's what the...
yeah, don't get hung up. Okay, we didn't need the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* for that, we needed a פסוק pasuk.
*pasuk* for something else we don't know about.
No, that we said before, either the full sister or whatever. Okay,
now the גמרא gemara *Gemara* continues. Okay, so now we have the
case of what do you call... so now we're getting to lay
the parameters of when you bring a separate חטאת chatat *chatat* and
again, separate sin certainly, even the same act, regardless of how it's
sort of expressed in the תורה Torah *Torah*, and the one question
that we maybe don't have resolved is Charlie's question about same sin
but different act, different people. Okay, now we're going on to go
through the cases of the משנה mishna *Mishna* with who you get
כרת *karet* and again with an eye towards what you bring a
חטאת chatat. *chatat*. הבא על הזכור *Haba al hazachor*, if a man
has sex with another man. I didn't get a chance to check,
but from what I remember, Michael asked the question why it says
זכור *zachor* not זכר *zachar*, that זכור *zachor* is used particularly for
the man that is penetrated, not for the man that is penetrating.
Okay, so that's a way of sort of identifying which person in
the act you're referring to. So let's take a look at the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. תנא tana במאי קחשיב *Tana b'mai kachashiv*? Now here
we get Rivka, your question, or your point you made yesterday. תנא
במאי קחשיב *Tana b'mai kachashiv*? Who's what type of a person, the
actor, is the תנא *Tana* talking about? Man or woman? Okay, now
the reason that why can't you say both, it's sort of flipping,
is because we said the whole point of giving a number was
to tell you you could bring these many חטאות chatatot, *chataot*. Okay,
but then it needs to be talking about one person could bring
those number of חטאות chatatot, *chataot* in one state. But it can't
all be done by one person. Why can't it all be done
by one person? Because אי בגברא *ei b'gavra*, if we're talking
about a man doing all of these acts and he could bring
thirty-four חטאות chatatot, *chataot*, so דל אשה ונרבע *dal isha v'nirva*, so
you don't have the case about a woman who had sex with
an animal, ובת לזכר *u'vas l'zachar*, and then you don't have thirty-four,
you only have thirty-three, you take away one. אי בנשי קחשיב *Ei
b'nashi kachashiv*, if it's talking about women, and although all of the
עריות *arayot* are described from the man's perspective, but if we are
talking about the woman of those acts and therefore the whole משנה
mishna *Mishna* talking about a woman doing these things, but then you
don't have דמינא הבא על הזכור *damina haba al hazachor*, you don't
have the case about sex with a man, דל בהמה behema? *dal
behema*, or sex with a בהמה behema? *behema*, which means
that the person is penetrated. penetrating the בהמה, behema right, as opposed
to מביא בהמה עליה. mayvi behema aleha. So therefore you have two
fewer that you can't have by a
woman, ובטילו תרתי, ubatilu tartei, you have two fewer. So you're never
going to get one person that's going to be all
34. So אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rabbi Yochanan לעולם תנא גברי le'olam
tana gavrei we're talking about one man. So how do you do
with the case
about בהמה? behema, ותני הכי vetani hachi הבא על הזכר והביא זכר
עליו. haba al hazachar vehevi zachar alav So ותני והביא זכר עליו
vetani vehevi zachar alav exactly for the reason I just said to
Michael, which is I believe what the והמביא זכר vehamayvi zachar no
okay והמביא זכר vehamayvi zachar okay it doesn't actually. Anyway, so he
says we're talking about when it says a woman who brings an
animal on her, actually he says that's not really what either he's
changing the text or says it's a euphemism, it's not what it
means. It's really saying that a man who has another man penetrate
him, that does that act. So meaning two separate acts, we're considering
those two separate עבירות aveirot and two separate and two separate חטאות
chatatot. for the man who is doing who does again I don't
know whether fine I'll say passive and active but that's not exactly
accurate but you'll know what I mean. Anyway, for the one who
is the more active or and the one who's the more passive
in the act, those are considered not to be the same עבירה,
aveira, those are distinct עבירות aveirot and therefore distinct חטאות. chatatot, So
if a person does both acts, okay, both you know both sort
of roles or positions whatever, then in that case it would be
two separate חטאות chatatot not one.
What does
it do with the בהמה? Behemah It doesn't. So בהמה he either
he said it didn't mean it, it was a euphemism, funny euphemism,
but or he's saying that maybe it was that wasn't the real
text in the משנה. mishna, So the text in the משנה mishna
was about bringing somebody bringing causing to be penetrated, but it was
and maybe that normally the case we imagine about that is the
case of a woman and a בהמה, but really that wasn't what
the משנה mishna was. It was talking about a homosexual act. Yes,
exactly, a man causing himself to be penetrated by another man. No,
it is, but we're trying to get a question nobody's denying that
you get כרת for these things and חטאת, chatat. but since we're
saying that the point of this list is to say you can
bring these many חטאות chatatot, in one state, how do you get
one person doing all of these things? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says now is that really two separate things and two separate קרבנות?
So the גמרא Gemara says yes actually that's a debate, but this
is who our משנה mishna. is going like, רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael,
and it's רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael who we know in סנהדרין Sanhedrin
says this, דאמר חייב שתים de'amar chayav shtayim that if that those
are two separate sins and two separate חטאות chatatot? based on the
two types of roles that a person could be playing.
That answers the question about 36 because if you don't count the
one that's מדרבנן miderabbanan in the משנה mishna then you only have
35.
No, anyway we only had 34 because you can't get פסח pesach
and מילה. mila.
All right, but you count those so count those. Right, but the
משנה mishna said 36 but one of them is clearly not
not well you know there could be 36. No, no, no, the
משנה mishna no, no, really if you took out the one in
parentheses you only had 35.
Yesterday maybe I counted wrong but it seemed that way.
Oh, I don't know. Charlie, you have the Artscroll, did it number
it? Did it number the one in parentheses or not?
No, it did not.
And it still got to 36?
It still got to 36.
Okay, so you can check the numbering. Okay, anyway, so let's take
a look. So anyway, if it was just the משנה, mishna if
we weren't claiming that one person could bring these number of חטאות,
chatatot, it wouldn't be a problem. You don't have to be one
person, these are just a list of the number of ways you
can get a חטאת. chatat. Okay, or you can get כרת. But
if we're saying one person, we have to describe it this way.
And it's רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael that says that those are separate
sins and separate חטאות. chatatot So the גמרא Gemara says one
minute, והא מדקתני מגדף בסיפא veha midekatani megadef besayfa at the end
of the משנה mishna one of the cases
is מגדף, megadef, blaspheming, ואוקמינא לה כרבי עקיבא ve'okmina lah kerabbi akiva
we're going to later say that that is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
because if you remember the last line of the משנה mishna says
oh no, no, no, things that don't do an action aren't included.
You might remember that, it was a little cryptic line at the
end of the משנה. mishna So the question is can you ever
bring a חטאת chatat for a sin that is not an action?
Meaning מגדף, megadef, blaspheming is not considered an action. Yes, you got
כרת, could you bring a חטאת? chatat And we're going to say
that that is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who says that yes you
can.
Okay, we'll be having in סנהדרין עקימת שפתיו הוי מעשה. Sanhedrin akimat
sefatav havei ma'aseh.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay, so we'll don't worry, we'll get to it.
So for other purposes we say the end of the משנה mishna
is רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who allows you to bring a who
allows you to say you bring a חטאת chatat? even for a
verbal act. And that's another רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva which we're going
to see later. So once that's רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, רישא נמי
רבי עקיבא, reisha nami Rabbi Akiva, the רישא reisha would have to
be רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva we're going
to see in a minute argues with רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael and
says that in both roles it's considered the same sin. וכי תימא
רבי עקיבא היא וברישא סבר לה כרבי ישמעאל. vechi teima Rabbi Akiva
hi uvereisha savar lah kerabbi Yishmael. Now let's say you'll say oh
maybe רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva holds like רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael about
considering those two separate acts, two separate
sins. No, ואמר רבי אבהו, ve'amar Rabbi Abbahu, הבא על הזכר haba
al hazachar והביא זכר עליו vehevi zachar alav. again if the person
does sort of both roles, the passive and the active, again using
those terms in quote marks, anyway in homosexual in you know in
the homosexual act those are are they is it one חטאת chatat.
or two? So he says רבי ישמעאל דמפיק להו מתרי קראי. Rabbi
Yishmael demafik lehu mitrei kray. . חייב שתים. chayav shtayim. So according
to him the fact that he learns it out from two פסוקים
pesukim means it would be two separate things and therefore two separate
חטאות. chatatot But Rabbi Akiva disagrees. לרבי עקיבא אינו חייב אלא אחת.
lerabbi akiva eino chayav ela achat. He only gets it once, it's
one sin and therefore would only be one חטאת. chatat You can't
say you only kill him once because okay anyway only one חטאת.
chatat מחד קרא נפיק ליה. mimichad kra nafik lei. You learn it
from one פסוק. pasuk. את זכר לא תשכב. et zachar lo tishkav.
So do not sleep. וקרי ביה vekarei beih and you can also
read it not לא תשכיב lo tashkiv which actually doesn't make sense
but the way the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet says it is לא
תשכב. lo tishachav. You shall not allow yourself to be slept with
as it were. Okay so he learns it from basically the one
פסוק. pasuk So therefore the משנה mishna can't be you can't say
that because it can't be the משנה mishna can't be Rabbi Akiva
because Rabbi Akiva would not allow you the end of the משנה
mishna is Rabbi Akiva but the beginning can't be Rabbi Akiva you're
not going to get two separate acts. So the גמרא Gemara: says
אלא ela fine. רישא reisha Rabbi Yishmael. So the beginning is like
we said Rabbi Yishmael we've replaced the case of the woman with
the animal with this case and therefore gives us our extra act
and our extra חטאת. chatat. ובמגדף סבר לה כרבי עקיבא. ubemegadef savar
lah kerabbi akiva. Rather than Rabbi Akiva holds like Rabbi Yishmael you
say Rabbi Yishmael holds like Rabbi Akiva. So fine the author of
the משנה Mishnah is Rabbi Yishmael that's the two separate acts and
when you get to the end about מגדף megadef that you bring
a חטאת chatat for a verbal act there Rabbi Yishmael will hold
like Rabbi Akiva. Okay and you don't bring you don't bring a
חטאת chatat. for a verbal act. No you do. You do. The
משנה Mishnah says that you do. It ended with a with an
opposing voice but the סתם משנה stam mishna said you do. We
were saying that's Rabbi Akiva so now we're saying fine it'll be
Rabbi Yishmael also. So according to Rabbi Akiva who learns it all
from that one פסוק pasuk does he say the קדש kadesh thing?
Does he mean that that's a woman? No generally that's not how
it's interpreted whether there's an איסור issur is another conversation. Okay. ובמגד...
so now the גמרא Gemara continues like this. אלא ela fine we
did that. אי הכי ניתני נמי הבא על הבהמה והביא בהמה עליו.
i hachi nisni nami haba al habehemah veheivi behemah alav. So if
you're going to get two separate acts so why are you ending
with thirty-six? You can get thirty-seven because the man could be the
passive or the receptive in terms of even if it's talking about
a man not talking about a woman he could play both roles
with an animal so therefore you'll get thirty-seven. Won't that also be
two separate things if by if a man and a man is
that way? אמר אביי amar Abaye no אביי Abaye says הבא על
הבהמה והביא בהמה עליו אף לרבי ישמעאל." haba al habehemah veheivi behemah
alav af lerabbi yishmael. "lo tishachav" is the passive reading of "lo
tishkav" (לא תשכב). lo tishachav. "megadef" (מגדף). megadef "chata'ot" (חטאות). chata'os, "chayav
shtayim" (חייב שתים). chayav shtayim. "reisha" (רישא). reisha "stam mishna" (סתם משנה).
stam mishna "i hachi" (אי הכי). "nisni nami" (ניתני נמי). "Rabbi Yishmael
learns from two פסוקים pesukim? this. Where does he learn the two
פסוקים? pesukim. From ואת זכר לא תשכב. ve'et zachar lo tishkav. So
the act of doing the active act, in quotes, is with a
male one should not sleep. So again, and by the way, it's
not only the fact that it's talking about the act of sex,
which is normally understood from the male perspective as the act of
penetration, it's also from the fact that I believe or I would
say that the end of the פסוק pasuk. says משכבי אשה, mishkevei
isha, which means which seems to be emphasizing like you the one
who are sleeping are sleeping as if you would be sleeping with
a woman. So it is referring to the actor is the one
who is penetrating and the one being acted upon as it were
is the one who is being penetrated. So that's the משכבי אשה.
mishkevei isha. So there we learn that act from. And then it
says and what's the other פסוק pasuk we learn from from doing
from from being the more quote unquote passive or being penetrated? ולא
יהיה קדש מבני ישראל. mivelo yiheyeh kadesh mibnei yisrael. That there shall
be no prostitute amongst בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. What does that mean
in the male? So he understands that means to be the to
be the you know to be the one who is penetrated in
the homosexual act, which is interesting. Like a female. All right, I
don't know because that's קדשה, kadesha, I don't know. No, so he
said... All right, so I don't know, that's a discussion in סנהדרין,
Sanhedrin, but that's what he learns from that. So the I would
just point out by the way interestingly though that again you could
research this but I believe in Rome, ancient Rome, which is not
the context of the תורה, Torah but anyway one wonders if you
can sort of extrapolate to other societies where homosexuality was widespread and
accepted, nevertheless there was a very different sort of role and identity
to the one that was the one who had penetrated versus one
who was penetrator and the one who was being penetrated was often
a slave, a prostitute, a servant, you know something of that sort
of a lower status, a lower status who is being the way
it was seen was sort of being used by the other person.
So to describe to say that this is what we learn from
קדש kadesh and this is how it's sort of being conceptualized you
can certainly understand how it's being framed that way.
Yes, still just still that distinction still exists today much of the
world.
Really? Very interesting. Even even within sort of you know places in
which like gay identity is embraced,
you are not gay unless you are the receptive partner. Interesting.
Yeah, very interesting.
That's the way they conceive it.
But is there still this difference about sort of that you know
that that's sort of like a seen as a more lowly like
like it's a negative kind of connotation
to be the receptive partner. Interesting. Interesting. Okay.
So he learns it out from two פסוקים. pesukim חייב שתים. So
according to him the fact that he learns it out from two
פסוקים means it would be two separate things and therefore two separate
חטאות. chata'os, But Rabbi Akiva disagrees. לרבי עקיבא אינו חייב אלא אחת.
lerabbi akiva eino chayav ela achat. He only gets it once, it's
one sin and therefore would only be one חטאת. chatat You can't
say you only kill him once because okay anyway only one חטאת.
chatat מחד קרא נפיק ליה. mimichad kra nafik lei. You learn it
from one פסוק. את זכר לא תשכב. et zachar lo tishkav. So
do not sleep. וקרי ביה vekarei beih and you can also read
it not לא תשכיב lo tashkiv which actually doesn't make sense but
the way the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzet says it is לא תשכב.
lo tishkav You shall not allow yourself to be slept with as
it were. Okay so he learns it from basically the one פסוק.
So therefore the משנה Mishnah, can't be you can't say that because
it can't be the משנה can't be Rabbi Akiva because Rabbi Akiva
would not allow you the end of the משנה is Rabbi Akiva
but the beginning can't be Rabbi Akiva you're not going to get
two separate acts. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא Ela, fine. רישא
Rabbi Yishmael. So the beginning is like we said Rabbi Yishmael we've
replaced the case of the woman with the animal with this case
and therefore gives us our extra act and our extra חטאת. chatat
ובמגדף סבר לה כרבי עקיבא. ubemegadef savar lah kerabbi akiva. Rather than
Rabbi Akiva holds like Rabbi Yishmael you say Rabbi Yishmael holds like
Rabbi Akiva. So fine the author of the משנה is Rabbi Yishmael
that's the two separate acts and when you get to the end
about מגדף that you bring a חטאת chatat for a verbal act
there Rabbi Yishmael will hold like Rabbi Akiva.
Okay and you don't bring you don't bring a חטאת chatat for
a verbal act.
No you do. You do. The משנה says that you do. It
ended with a with an opposing voice but the סתם משנה said
you do. We were saying that's Rabbi Akiva so now we're saying
fine it'll be Rabbi Yishmael also.
So according to Rabbi Akiva who learns it all from that one
פסוק does he say the קדש kadesh thing? Does he mean that
that's a woman?
No generally that's not how
it's interpreted whether there's
an איסור issur is another
No, even
Rabbi Yishmael who has said as two separate
for the man, he will have it not as two separate with
this case with the animal. Because why? Because you don't have an
extra פסוק there. דכתיב קרא בגבי דקרא. De-ketiv kra be-gavei de-kra. This
idea of לא תשכב and קדש kadesh or whatever, those are all
talking about with men. It is not talking about with animals, that
is all one פסוק. Okay. So now, so fine. So therefore the
משנה works. That's one answer. That we take out the case of
the woman and we replace it with two different cases of two
men. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: רבי אליעזר משמיה
דרבא אמר, Rabbi Eliezer mishmei de-Rava amar, we're still trying to get
another answer to the question of how do you have one person
bringing doing all of these? תני שלשים ושלש חטאות. Tani sheloshim ve-shalosh
chatatot.
Fine. Okay. Not 34, 33. Anyways, not 36. It's not פסח Pesach
and מילה. Milah. So, although the point of the משנה is to
tell you bring separate חטאות, chata'os. we never said that one person
is going to bring them all. Fine. One person will bring 33.
ותני שלשים ושש כריתות וסיומי בכריתות, Ve-tani sheloshim ve-shesh keritot ve-siyumei be-keritot,
and it gives you the other three to tell you there's 36
כריתות. keritot. Okay, but one person will only be able to bring
33 חטאות, chata'os, you know, in one at one time. Okay, דתני,
de-tani, how do I know that it's not all about a חטאת?
chatat Cause two of them certainly are not about a חטאת. chatat.
סיפא פסח ומילה במצות עשה. Seifa Pesach u-Milah be-mitzvot asei. פסח ומילה,
Pesach u-Milah, those are positive מצות עשה. פסח ומילה אמאי תני להו?
Pesach u-Milah amai tani lehu? Why is it telling? אי תימא לאתויי
קרבן עליהו, I teima le-atuyei korban alaihu, if you say that you
could bring a קרבן for the non-doing of a פסח ומילה, Pesach
u-Milah, that's not true. מי מייתי? Mi mayit? Since when do you
bring a קרבן for not doing a positive מצוה? mitzvah? ותניא, Ve-tanya,
תנא ברייתא: tana baraita: הוקש כל התורה כולה לעבודת כוכבים. Hukesh kol
ha-Torah kullah le-avodat kochavim. The whole תורה Torah, is in terms of
bringing a חטאת chatas. is linked to the case in the תורה
bringing a חטאת chatas for עבודה זרה בשוגג. avodah zarah be-shogeg. דכתיב:
De-ketiv: תורה אחת יהיה לכם לעושה בשגגה. Torah achat yihyeh lachem la-oseh
bi-shgagah. One law, if you do בשגגה be-shgagah you bring a חטאת.
chatas? And then it says: והנפש אשר תעשה ביד רמה את ה'
הוא מגדף. Ve-ha-nefesh asher ta'aseh be-yad ramah, et Hashem hu megadef.
So somebody who, you know, who does with an outstretched arm, which
is understood to mean does an act of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
So it says, it juxtaposes bringing a חטאת chatas, with an act
of עבודה זרה avodah zarah to tell you that is the paradigm
if done בשוגג be-shogeg when you bring a חטאת. chatas. That by
the way is why there's a debate of does it have to
be a physical act? Cause עבודה זרה avodah zarah is a physical
act. What if it's only a verbal act? That's the debate we're
going to see we mentioned before and we're going to look at
later. But here, the first certainly the thing we do know from
that is it's only if you're talking about a violation, not if
you're talking about non-performance. You never bring a חטאת Chatas for not
doing a positive מצוה. mitzvah.
So,
does פיגול pigul apply only to the person who's doing the עבודה?
avodah?
Yes, but
well no, no, the eating of פיגול pigul applies to everybody. The
act of פיגול pigul and the act of פיגול pigul is not
the כרת, the כרת is only for the eating of פיגול. pigul.
Okay. But you were trying to think if it had to be
a כהן? kohen? Okay. So anyways, the גמרא Gemara says like this:
מה עבודת כוכבים שב ואל תעשה, ma avodat kochavim shev ve-al ta'aseh,
so certainly what we learn is the same way about עבודה זרה
avodah zarah your obligation is to not do. It's a funny way
of saying that, but anyway, your obligation is to not do. אף
שב ואל תעשה. af shev ve-al ta'aseh. The only time you bring
a חטאת Chatas is when you were violating your obligation to not
do, not if you were violating your, not if you were not
fulfilling your responsibility to do. אלא לאו שמע מינה, Ella lav shema
mina, so therefore you're never going to get 36 חטאות, chata'os, which
is so funny because we've been saying that from the beginning, right?
And the גמרא: Gemara 36? What about פסח? Pesach? So finally he
says, okay, what about פסח ומילה? Pesach u-Milah? So you're not going
to get 36 anyway. שמע מינה תני שלשים ושלש חטאות. shema mina
tana sheloshim ve-shalosh chatatot. So therefore we're not talking about, we never
gave you a specific number for how many חטאות. chata'os? So fine,
one person can only get 33. מאן דעביד בשוגג, Man de-avid be-shogeg,
if you did it בשוגג. be-shogeg. והדר תני שלשים ושש כריתות, Ve-hadar
tani sheloshim ve-shesh keritot, and then we gave you three more וסיומי
בכריתות ve-siyumei be-keritot to give you the full number of כריתות, keritot,
שמע מינה. So although the context, although this is מסכת כריתות, Masechet
Keritot, the context is it could have just as easily been called
מסכת חטאות, Masechet Chatatot, cause the reason it starts with כריתות keritot
is to tell you and get to the issue of your חטאת
Chatas? obligations. He's pointing out fine, but it's not all about your
חטאת chatas. obligation, we're giving you the full story of 36 כריתות.
keritot. In the same way two are not חטאות, chata'os the one
of them also maybe it is a חטאת actually, interestingly, but it's
not all חטאות chata'os? with one person. Again, he's not saying that
there are only 33 חטאות, there are 34, but since when are
we saying that one person is going to bring 36 חטאות? He's
not going to bring 36, he also won't bring 34, he'll bring
33. Okay, so you're
saying it depends on what the woman wants or something? Right. It
is a חטאת for... Okay, good. Now we've got that settled, that
it's not necessarily 34 חטאות, it's not necessarily all one person, and
now we're going to move on the משנה, yes?
These guys have agreed that being the passive actor in the homosexual...
That's the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi
Yishmael.
What you know, this
is...
It is, depends on if you bring a חטאת. Who knows?
Depends on their debate, depends on which way you פסקן pasken that
debate. So meaning it might be 35.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara goes on. המחלל את השבת. Ha-mechallel et
ha-Shabbat.
Now if that weren't enough to add to the list, how about
we're now going to get to שבת. Shabbat. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: אמרי שבת מ"ם חסר אחת הוי. Amri Shabbat mem
chaser achat havei. What do you mean? שבת Shabbat counts as one.
If you're talking about how many חטאות you could bring, you can
bring 39 חטאות for שבת. Shabbat. If you forgot each מלאכה, melacha,
you remembered it was שבת, Shabbos, you forgot all the מלאכות, melachos,
okay, you still remembered it was שבת, Shabbos, like you remembered תחומים
techumim or something. Anyway, you remembered, you forgot all the מלאכות, melachos,
you could bring 39 חטאות, each one is considered a separate sin.
So for lifting, trying to get a high, the number of חטאות,
it's much more than 36. 39 different חטאות. So אמר רבי יוחנן,
Amar Rabbi Yochanan, תנא שגגת שבת וזדון מלאכות. tana shigas Shabbos vezadon
melachos. So we're not talking about that case. We're not talking about
that you forgot the מלאכות. melachos. We're talking about you forgot it
was שבת, Shabbos, you thought it was Sunday. And therefore, because it
was one thing you forgot, that it was שבת, Shabbos, it's considered
one act of חילול שבת chilul Shabbos done multiple times. Not considered
to be 39 different types of עבירות, averot, because what you forgot
was שבת, Shabbos, and therefore you only bring one חטאת. Okay, דלא
מחייב אלא חדא, delo mechayev ela chada, then you only bring one,
דתניא. detanya. And now we're going to talk about that idea about
whether you bring one or 39.
מהנה שהיא אחת. heina shehi achas. The פסוק says אשר יעשה מאחת
מהנה, asher ye'aseh mei'achas meiheina, does from one from these. So the
גמרא's Gemara. דרש drash is it doesn't say אחת מהנה, achas meiheina,
one of these. It says מאחת מהנה, mei'achas meiheina, from one from
one of these. So there we learn that there sometimes is one
type of a sin that counts as that basically counts as multiple
חטאות, multiple sins, and sometimes multiple that counts as one. What does
that mean? So מהנה שהיא אחת, heina shehi achas, sometimes you do
multiple things but it really only counts as one. What's that scenario?
שגגת שבת וזדון מלאכות. shigagat Shabbos vezadon melachos. You forgot it was
שבת. Shabbos. So you could have you could have known that all
39 מלאכות melachos are אסור assur on שבת, Shabbos, done all 39
of them, you did 39 distinct things, it counts as one, it
counts as one חילול שבת chilul Shabbos because what you forgot was
that it was שבת. Shabbos. ונתני זאת, venisni zot, okay, that's why
we only have one. But says okay, but if we're looking to
give you a full number, why didn't we give the other example?
ונתני זדון שבת ושגגת מלאכות, venisni zedon Shabbos veshigagat melachos, why not
give the example you knew it was שבת Shabbos and you forgot
the מלאכות, melachos, which will give you 39 separate acts? דמחייב מ"ם
חסר אחת, demechayev mem chaser achas, that then you will bring 39
חטאות, דתניא. detanya. Here's the full ברייתא. braisa. ועשיתם מאחת מהנה, ve'asitem
mei'achas meiheina, פסק, pasak, excuse me,
and you shall do from one from these. פעמים שחייב אחת על
כולן, pe'amim shechayav achas al kulan, sometimes you bring you bring only
one חטאת for מהנה, heina,
for many different acts. פעמים שחייב על כל אחת ואחת, pe'amim shechayav
al kol achas ve'achas, and sometimes you bring for each separate act.
אחת שהיא מהנה, achas shehi heina, what's a case of one act
which is multiple? It's not really one, it's multiple, but when is
it that you bring multiple חטאות? זדון שבת ושגגת מלאכות, zedon Shabbos
veshigagat melachos,
if you knew it was שבת Shabbos and you forgot the מלאכות,
melachos, then you bring distinct חטאות for each distinct מלאכה. melacha. So
anyway, so now that we see that depending you can have both
scenarios, why did our תנא list only the forgetting of שבת, Shabbos,
which only gives you one חטאת? Why didn't he list forgetting the
מלאכות, melachos, which could give you a scenario of 39 חטאות? So
the גמרא Gemara says, תנא דידן שגגת שבת וזדון מלאכות עדיפא ליה.
tana didan shigagat Shabbos vezadon melachos adifa lei.
He'd rather mention the case of forgetting שבת. Shabbos. Why? דמחטאת מיהא
לא מיפטר. demichatas miya lo miftar. Because at least you know that
you're going to always bring one חטאת, which means what? It's a
little unclear. One of the רש"י Rashi has two explanations. One of
the things רש"י Rashi says is if I said 39 separate מלאכות,
melachos, that's not always true that it's always going to be 39.
Why? Even if you did 39 acts. Because let's say you forgot
both. You both forgot it was שבת Shabbos and you forgot that
these things were אסור assur on שבת. Shabbos. So how do we
categorize that? So the general there's a question about that but generally
we assume that that's considered since forgetting of שבת Shabbos was sufficient,
we define it by your forgetting of שבת Shabbos and therefore it's
only one חטאת. So we didn't want to say 39 because that
wouldn't necessarily always be 39. If you also forgot it was שבת,
Shabbos, it would all collapse to one.
So we wanted to give one. But we can also have 71
either?
No, it'll always be one. If you forget שבת Shabbos it'll always
be one. So by שבת Shabbos we said one because it could
be the other number could fluctuate, but you're always going to have
one.
בפשטא רובא b'pashta ruba basically.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, alright, oh my
gosh, we are falling more and more behind, these דפים daptim are
too thick.
We're falling more behind being...
Alright, anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this, דמחטאת מיהא לא מיפטר.
demichatas miya lo miftar. וכן אתה מוצא, vechein ata motzei,
let's just try to speed at least the case of עבודה זרה.
avodah zarah. This is a fascinating case. וכן אתה מוצא גבי
עבודת כוכבים, vechein ata motzei gabei avodas kochavim, by עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah. דתני, detani, that you can have multiple and you can have
one. You could A, forget that עבודה זרה avodah zarah is אסור,
assur, or the other thing is you can bring separate separate things
for separate acts of עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
Slaughtering an animal, you know, sort of burning, you know, doing הקטרה,
haktara, bowing down, all those are considered as, yeah, distinct acts of
עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. So if you remembered that עבודה זרה avodah
zarah was אסור assur but you didn't realize that those acts were
forbidden, I don't know what you thought was forbidden, but okay, you
didn't realize oh, I didn't know that was forbidden, anyway, then that
would be multiple, those would be considered distinct sins. If you forgot
about עבודה זרה avodah zarah and you did all those things, then
they would all be considered one thing. Very parallel to... The גמרא's
Gemara going to talk about what you didn't know. Let's read the
גמרא. Gemara Okay, וכן אתה מוצא גבי עבודת כוכבים דתני. vechein ata
motzei gabei avodas kochavim detani. שגגת עבודת כוכבים, shigagat avodas kochavim,
if you forgot that עבודה זרה avodah zarah was אסור, assur, וזדון
עבודות, vezadon avodot, but you knew that those things were forbidden acts.
Now how could you forget עבודה זרה avodah zarah is אסור assur
and know those were forbidden acts? That's what the גמרא's Gemara going
to talk about. Or שגגת עבודות, shigagat avodot,
so now the גמרא Gemara immediately interrupts. שגגת עבודת כוכבים היכי דמי?
shigagat avodas kochavim heichi dami? What does that mean that you forgot
about... Your mistake was about the עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, and you
knew these were still forbidden acts. אילימא דאמר בבית עבודת כוכבים וסבר
בבית הכנסת
הוא והשתחוה, Eilema D'amar Be-veit Avodas Kochavim Ve-savar Be-veit Haknesset Hu Ve-hishtachaveh,
let's say you were in a church, oh I shouldn't say that,
let's say you were in a temple of Zeus and then we
won't talk about Christianity halakhic tough discussion right now. You were in
a temple of Zeus but you thought you were in a שול
Shul and you bowed down. So bowing down is an act of
עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, but you thought you didn't realize you were
being עובד Oveid עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So the גמרא Gemara says
so that's a case where it's forgetting and you did multiple different
acts. So the גמרא Gemara... says and then you slaughtered a בהמה
right? Anyway, okay, moving on. הרי לבו לשמים. Harei libo lashamayim. The
גמרא Gemara says the fact that there happened to be you happened
to be in a temple of Zeus and an idol of Zeus
was in front of you does not define it as an act
of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah if you're praying to God. Okay? Just
physically that you're doing this act in front of an idol of
Zeus and in the temple, if you're praying to God it is
not an act of עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah.
תוספות Tosafot asks over here now, well
that does raise very important questions about martyrdom. Why are all of
these things תוספות Tosafot asks these, why is there an obligation of
martyrdom if in the end of the day you're not really believing?
Okay now that's a little different. One thing is you're praying to
God, the other is you're going through the actions without really holding
the beliefs but you're still directing your actions to this you know
to this עבודה. Avodah. So A, it's a little different there, but
even in that we'll see in a minute that also might not
be עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So then the idea of martyrdom is
more about the קידוש השם Kiddush Hashem aspect, it's more about the
visible aspect than it is about whether it is technically the act
of עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. But that's a I didn't say that.
That is a different it's not עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. That is
a different discussion but it's obviously the right question to ask.
So anyway you could דאוון Daven in I'm not answering that question.
You're not doing
עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. ואלא דחזא אנדרטא, Ve-ela de-chaza andartas, so maybe
the case is that you saw a statue. וסגיד לה. Ve-sagid lah.
אנדרטא Andartas means not an idol, a statue, and you bow down
to it. So that was a case where you didn't think you
were doing anything wrong. You were giving fealty to the statue of
the king. But the גמרא says still make up your mind. אי
דקבליה לאלוה, Iy de-kablih le-eloah, if you
treated that statue as your god, so פשיטא, Pashitah, then you're willfully
worshipping עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. What do you mean it's a שוגג?
Shogeg? ואי דלא קבליה לאלוה, Ve-iy de-lo kablih le-eloah, if you just
bowed down to the statue to show your respect, not because you
treated it as a god, לאו מידי הוא, Lav midy hu, then
you didn't do עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So you still don't have
a case where you did it but you didn't realize it was
אסור. Asur. You didn't realize you were doing עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah.
אלא מאהבה ומיראה. Ela me-ahavah u-miyirah. How about if you worshipped it
and this is the case תוספות Tosafot asks, you worshipped it not
that you're worshipping God, but you're doing this act but not because
you really believe. You're doing it for ulterior motives. You're doing it
מיראה Miyirah because there's a sword
to no no to
a real idol of Zeus here. מאהבה Me-ahavah because because you love
somebody, you want to marry somebody, or maybe רש"י Rashi says you
want to advance in society, or יראה, Yirah, somebody's holding a gun
to your head, you're afraid of somebody, so you're doing the act
to this idol of Zeus but you don't really believe. Now that
actually is and you think that's okay. You think that's not עבודה
זרה. Avodah Zarah. That's okay. And therefore that's your שוגג. Shogeg. You
thought it was okay under those circumstances. So the גמרא says okay,
בהני ניחא לאביי דאמר חייב. Be-hani nicha le-Abaye de-amar chayav. So according
to אביי he says under those circumstances it is עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah and your mistake was you thought it wasn't. And therefore you
are עובד Oveid עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah בשוגג, Be-shogeg, that was one
multiple different ways, that was still one mistake. אלא לרבא דאמר פטור,
Ela le-Rava de-amar patur, but רבא Rava says it's not עבודה זרה
Avodah Zarah and that is the whole question of the question of
martyrdom. But if that is not עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, so again
you shouldn't have done it but you didn't do עבודה זרה. Avodah
Zarah. So where is the case? So let's just see the answer.
מאי איכא למימר? Mai ika le-meimar? אלא, let's just end with the
answer, באומר מותר. Be-omer mutar. You actually you knew it was an
act of עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, but you thought that you never
read the תורה, you thought that you're allowed to be עובד Oveid
עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. Okay? You knew all these things were separate
acts of עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, but you thought that it was
permissible. So therefore that is one mistake and therefore you bring only
one חטאת although you do those distinct acts. Now the point is
I'll just read one more sentence. דעד כאן לא קבעי מיניה רבא
מרב נחמן אלא אי חדא מחייבי תרתי מחייבי. De-ad kan lo ka-ba'ei
mineih Rava me-Rav Nachman ela iy echada mechayvei tartei mechayvei. If you
if you thought that both the general category was permissible and because
the general category you thought it was you also made mistakes about
the particulars. This is like the example you thought it was Sunday
and you forgot all these things were מלאכות. Melachot. Do we is
that one חטאת or multiple חטאת? So this is the same. If
you didn't know עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah was אסור, Asur, then you
also didn't know that these separate acts were אסור. Asur. Okay? So
is that so there the question is you bring one or do
you bring multiple? So there the question of אמיפטר לגמרי לא בעי
מיניה. Amiftar legamrei lo ba'ei mineih. Obviously you minimally bring one. So
therefore what's the scenario where you're going to make a mistake by
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah besides making a mistake about the acts? Is
that you thought עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah was מותר. I should say
though importantly this is גמרא is against what רש"י Rashi said on
pseudo-רש"י said on the on the first דף. Daf. There he said
באומר מותר Be-omer mutar is an אונס. Ones. But here the גמרא...
said again, maybe it depends on context. Maybe אומר מותר omer mutar
for מפתה mefateh and סוכך sochech is an אונס, ones, but אומר
מותר omer mutar for עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah is certainly not an
אונס. ones. So it's at least a שוגג. shogeg. And that's an
important question in general, if you think you are completely ignorant of
the law, is that what category does that put you in? Here
the גמרא says it puts you in שוגג shogeg and minimally you
would bring one חטאת.